Good morning, חודש טוב *Chodesh Tov*. Today's דף *daf* is נ"ה *Nun
Hey*. We pick up on the middle of נ"ד עמוד ב' nun-daled
amud bet, *Nun Dalet Amud Bet*. We had a fascinating גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* that dealt with the issue of the כרובים *Keruvim* and the
sort of erotic aspect of that, at least intimate aspect of that,
and the significance of the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol *Kohen Gadol* going
into the innermost chamber, הביאני המלך חדריו חדריו *Heviani HaMelech Chadarav, Chadarav*,
and the sort of the even the use of the word ביאה
*Bi'ah*, the putting of the incense between the בדים *Badim*, quoting the
פסוק pasuk *Pasuk* from the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* from the שיר השירים
*Shir HaShirim*, צרור המור דודי לי בין שדי ילין *Tzror HaMor Dodi
Li Bein Shaday Yalin*, very powerful imagery, and also how it can
be, you know, seen in the wrong context,
which was the end of the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*, sort of taken
out from the innermost and brought into the שוק *Shuk* and turned
almost, you know, made into a denigration. So sort of the power
of that imagery and also the sense of its hiddenness, which is
also very much about, you know, only the כהן גדול kohen gadol
*Kohen Gadol* only one day on יום כיפור Yom Kippur? *Yom Kippur*.
Of course, there was also fascinating that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* mentioned
on the רגלים *Regalim* that there was a certain revealing of it
to בני ישראל Yisrael, *Bnei Yisrael*. Before we continue, it's worth mentioning
that the huge תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* of כרובים דצורתא *Keruvim DeTzurta* that
starts on the beginning of נ"ד עמוד א' *Nun Dalet Amud Aleph*.
It goes a little bit off topic, but it's a very important
תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* about the whole issue about Jewish art because the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said that instead of the כרובים *Keruvim* on the
בית שני *Bayit Sheni*, what they did have was that they had
engravings of the כרובים *Keruvim* on the walls. Now, of course, what
they did in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash *Beit HaMikdash* is not
a good model for what you're allowed to do, like I would
not advise going ahead and making your own statues of כרובים *Keruvim*
in your own house, right? The whole issue there about what constitutes
the making of an image, of an idol, not an idol but,
you know, of a graven image,
and, you know, there's certain things like כהנים *Kohanim* also wore שעטנז
*Shatnez*, you know, certain latitude of what happened in the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash *Beit HaMikdash* is not always a good model.
But תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* though uses this as a jumping-off point for
raising this question and I just want to read you the beginning
of the תוספות *Tosafot* on נ"ד עמוד א' *Nun Dalet Amud Aleph*.
תוספות *Tosafot* says there, נשאלתי *Nishalti*, I was asked, על al אותם
שמציירים במחזורים צורת חיות ועופות *al otam she-metzayrim ba-machzorim tziyurat chayot ve-ofot*.
He's telling you a שאלה *shaylah* he got. I don't know who
the בעל תוספות *Ba'al Tosafot* is who wrote this. על al אותם
שמציירים במחזורים צורת חיות ועופות *al otam she-metzayrim ba-machzorim tziyurat chayot ve-ofot*
that they have, you know, pictures in the מחזורים *Machzorim*. And if
you've ever been to the, you know, to any of the Jewish
museum or sometimes, you know, whatever, the Metropolitan, you sometimes see these
Jewish illuminated מחזורים *Machzorim*, beautiful, and a lot of it is these
sort of, you know, these pastoral pictures, you know, and you have
animals and
they're not usually real, they're usually...
right, they usually do imaginary, right, and there's usually some change that's
done specifically to address these concerns. אם יפה עושים אם לאו *Im
yafeh osim im lav*. And that's correct, והשבתי *v'heshavti*, and I responded,
אלו דודאי לא יפה עושים *ilu d'vadai lo yafeh osim*. Now why
not? Why is this not appropriate? שמתוך שמסתכלים בציורים הללו אין מכוונים
ליבם לאבינו שבשמים *She-mitoch she-mistaklin be-tziyurim halalu ein mekavnim libam la-Avinu she-bashamayim*.
You're spending too much time looking at the pretty pictures and you're
not spending enough time דאוונען *davenning*. So that's why it's not acceptable.
מיהו *Mihu*, he says, אין כאן איסור דלא תעשה לך פסל *ein
kan issur de-lo ta'aseh lekha fesel*. It's not a violation of the
biblical commandment, דהמקצת כל צלמים שאנו רואים גומליות אחרים עשו לו *de-ha-miktzat
kol tzal-mim she-anu ro-im gumliyot acheirim asu lo*. So those are other
people made it. We have the people, we have to be assuming
are non-Jews because if Jews are making it, why does that make
it acceptable? For the Jews to make it. ואפילו חשדא ליכא *Ve-afillu
chashda lekka*, there's no concern about being suspected that maybe you're worshiping
it because in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* in עבודה avodah. זרה *Avodah
Zarah* it's clear that there's one issue of you making things and
what's included in the prohibition of לא תעשה לך *Lo Ta'aseh Lecha*,
and there's another problem about owning things that even if they're owned
for ornamental or aesthetic or other purposes, would people suspect you of
actually worshiping them? So תוספות *Tosafot* says there's no concern about being
suspected except what's the word... ליכא בציורים שהני מנצבעים
בעלמא *lekka betziyurim she-hani mi-nitzva'im be'alma*, these are just, you know, it's
just colors, it's paint, ואין בהם ממשות כלל *ve'ein ba-hem mamashut klal*,
it's not actually something of like three-dimensional, דלא חיישינן לחשדא אלא בחותם
בולט *d'lo chaishinan l'chashda ella be-chotam bolet*, has to be concerned about
חשדא *chashda*, it has to be something that's either engraved or something
that protrudes. And anyway he goes through the whole discussion here, very
wild תוספות *Tosafot* discussing what types of things might be problematic in
terms of Jewish art either because of לא תעשה לך פסל *Lo
Ta'aseh Lecha Pesel* actual statues or the way the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*
expands that category to include things that are, you know, human figures
or things that represent the celestial spheres and also concerns about when
even owning things are a problem because you might be suspected of
worshiping them which has a lot to do with the context of
what types of things are worshiped. So it's very worth knowing that
this is a very important תוספות *Tosafot* for discussions about the הלכה
*halakhic* issues around Jewish art where obviously I'm not going to go
through it now but I want you to be aware of it.
Rifka?
Yeah, maybe you mentioned before I came in. Would you say that
the image, the whole thing with the ארון Aron *Aron* and female
imagery, and clearly the כהן *Kohen* is male? Right. Would you say
that's very close to imagining God as female? We said that yesterday.
That was what we...
yeah, yesterday, yesterday we mentioned that a number of times that what's
shocking besides... The sort of eroticism that's so shocking and powerful about
yesterday's גמרא Gemara is that God is imagined as the female. God
is normally imagined as the male. Right, but here, God is the,
right? You have the, you have the ארון aron with the breasts
and the קודש קדשים Kodesh Kodashim and the whole גמרא Gemara. speaks
about כלה, kallah, היכן דדי שדיא, hichen dadei shadya, היכן דדי חמיא.
hichen dadei chamya. Right. God is the female. And it's so ironic
that women have been so distanced from the divine, which is itself
imagined as female.
Right, but that's again what makes this גמרא Gemara, an exception is
that it's very rare that that happens. Right, but yes, but it's
rare, but
here it is happening in the holiest. Right, I mean, when we're
speaking about that human-divine encounter, you're right,
to primarily to sort
of, you know, imagine
God as the female in that sense is...
Yeah, and yet distancing women from anything holy. Right? Now, I mean,
we're saying women aren't supposed to pray at the כותל. Kotel. Right,
right, right. But just to be fair, a lot of rabbis say
men shouldn't.
Yes, two more questions and then we have to move on.
Yes.
So photography then not to be excluded from...
Yeah, photography most, whatever the issues are with various issues of art,
from, you know, I mean,
photography is by almost all is excluded from those concerns because it's
not. But again, you know, I mean, if you have a problem
about three dimensions, about even like simple, you know, coloring illustration, you
know, I suppose it's possible but... anyway, it's a longer conversation. But
basically, yes, the biggest concerns are limited to those that are three-dimensional,
not those that...
Okay, good שיעור. shiur.
It is a good שיעור. shiur. Yeah.
I just think it's such a weird thought because to sit around,
I've seen this bench where a סידור Siddur is actually printed in
a contrasting color over a photograph of some place in Israel.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah. Which I thought was very... yeah, so
there you go.
Okay, one more constant short comment? Yeah. Just
all the Greek statues in the Hellenistic period were colored. They're not
alabaster.
Right, right, right, I know, I know. They've been doing the whole
restoration.
All still filled with color.
Right, but those are talking about just the colors, not the statues.
Okay, let's get back to the גמרא. Gemara ושתיה היתה נקראת. v’shitiyah
haytah nikreit. So that was a nice little digression, important little point,
but anyway, now, right, נד עמוד ב, two lines before the lines
get wide. ושתיה היתה נקראת. v’shitiyah haytah nikreit. So this stone was
called שתיה, Shitiyah, foundation stone. So the גמרא Gemara says, תנא, tanna,
שממנה הושתת העולם. shemimmenah hushtat ha-olam. From that stone the world was
founded, was built upon that stone. That was the sort of rock
that was the first part of the גמרא Gemara and the Torah...
the Torah spread out from there. תנן כמאן דאמר מציון נברא עולם.
tenan
k’man
d’amar mi-Tzion nivra olam. We taught like the position that says that
the world was created from ציון, Tzion, because this rock is in
ציון, Tzion, in Zion, on הר הבית. Har HaBayit.
So that was the first thing created and everything was built upon
that. דתניא, d’tanya, we taught in a
ברייתא: braita: רבי אליעזר אומר עולם מאמצעיתו נברא. Rabbi Eliezer omer olam
m’emtzaito nivra. The world was created from its middle. שנאמר, she-ne’emar, well
let's take a look. It's interesting. Okay, שנאמר, she-ne’emar, let's read it,
בצקת עפר למוצק, betzeket afar l’mutzak, when the pouring out of the
dirt of the dust for like the foundation, ורגבים
ידובקו, u-regavim yedubaku, and the clods of earth will be stuck together.
So somehow it means that, you know, that
there was like one foundation and everything was added to it. Basically,
it starts with something in the middle and everything is added. Michael
might be right, it might have a sense of like a core
and added, you know, around it from the outside.
How did you translate בצקת? betzeket?
The pouring out.
Right, yes. רבי יהושע אומר עולם מן הצדדין נברא. Rabbi Yehoshua omer
olam min ha-tzadadin nivra. No, it was created from the sides. שנאמר
כי לשלג יאמר הוי ארץ, she-ne’emar ki la-sheleg yomar hevei aretz, because
to the snow it says, be the land,
וגשם מטר וגשם מטרות עוזו, v’geshem matar v’geshem matrot uzo, and the
rain of and the pouring of rain and the pouring of the
rain of His strength. So what does that say? So
רש״י Rashi says, because when it says to the snow He said
it is land, it means the snow He said to make the
land. And somehow the snow made the land and the rain made
the land and all these different things somehow came together, you know,
from different sides all together to make the earth. I don't exactly
get it. רבי יצחק נפחא אומר אבן ירה הקדוש ברוך הוא בים.
Rabbi Yitzchak Nafcha omer even yara ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu ba-yam. God threw
a stone into the ocean.
ממנה נשתת העולם, mimmenah nishtat ha-olam, and from that stone the world
was created. שנאמר על מה אדניה
הטבעו, she-ne’emar al mah adaneha hotbe’u, on what were its
sockets, the foundation,
sunken in, או מי ירה אבן פנתה, o mi yara even pinatah,
who cast down the foundation stone. So it's something about cast... from
heaven down to the earth. Of course it says that there was
a ים yam before there was an earth. I don't know. But
anyway, but this obviously is the idea, you know, like cities rising
from the earth in the sense that most of the world is
ocean, you know, and that I mean even the story of בראשית,
Bereishit, it starts with ocean and the ocean is separated in order
for there to be earth.
You know, also the foundation of Rome, I
mean I was just you know reading about that. Exactly. So exactly,
the whole myth about the foundation of Rome. So the idea that
it starts with ocean and then somehow earth came rose up from
that. וחכמים אומרים מציון נברא העולם. Vachachamim omrim mi-Tzion nivra ha-olam. Not.
It was created from Zion. שנאמר מזמור לאסף, Shene'emar mizmor le-Asaf, a
song to Asaf, אל אלהים ה׳, El Elohim Hashem, God of Gods
is God, ואומר מציון מכלל יופי, ve-omer mi-Tzion michlal yofi, from Zion
from the epitome of
beauty, ממנו מכלל יפיו של עולם, mimenu michlal yofyo shel olam, from
it was established the glory of the world. So meaning the world
was created from Zion. So this is of course a you know
fascinating discussion. I mean, is it just like cosmology? Is it just
דורש doresh different פסוקים? pesukim? Are there just fundamentally different philosophies? You
know the idea Zion is from Zion the world was created? It
means that you know the whole purpose of not only you know
the whole purpose of creation is basically is you know you know
is the you know
the whole purpose of creation is for for ישראל, is for
is for Zion. You know the other the other you know the
other approach hold on one second I got distracted I see this
is not going to work. By all the beautiful pictures? What? Yeah
by all the beautiful pictures. Excuse me. Anyway I see this is
not going to work. Okay anyway, so so
what was I talking oh so you know one thing Zion is
like the standard very much Israel focus or Zion maybe not as
much Israel focus but Zion as the connection of God to the
earth. You know sort of the heavenly abode is connected above you
know to where the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. is below here. So
anyway a very sort of religious focusing and centering of the world
as opposed to some of these others. I don't know exactly what
to do with all the different opinions but but you know but
it seems a little more human-oriented than the Zion than the center
was all created from ציון. Tzion.
Okay so now the גמרא Gemara continues. תניא רבי אליעזר הגדול אומר,
Tanya Rabbi Eliezer ha-Gadol omer, אלה תולדות השמים והארץ בהבראם, eleh toldot
ha-shamayim ve-ha-aretz be-hibaram, these are the these are the you know the
stories of the heavens and earth when they were created. ביום עשות
ה׳ אלהים ארץ ושמים. Be-yom asot Hashem Elohim eretz ve-shamayim. תולדות שמים
משמים נבראו, Toldot shamayim mi-shamayim nivre'u, תולדות הארץ מארץ נבראו, toldot ha-aretz
me-eretz nivre'u, the generations of the heavens were created from the heaven
first God created the heaven and then everything else that came from
the heavens, the sun, the moon, the stars were somehow created you
know from the heavens themselves. And the generations of the land were
created from the land which you know the trees and the plants
and all of that sprouted up from the ground but presumably also
animals and humans, רש״י Rashi brings this down in his commentary on
בראשית. Bereishit. וחכמים אומרים אלו ואלו מציון נבראו. Vachachamim omrim elu ve-elu
mi-Tzion nivre'u. No, they were all created out of Zion. שנאמר מזמור
לאסף אל אלהים ה׳, Shene'emar mizmor le-Asaf El Elohim Hashem, דבר ויקרא
ארץ ממזרח שמש עד מבואו, diber va-yikra eretz mi-mizrach shemesh ad mevo'o,
ואומר מציון מכלל יופי אלהים הופיע, ve-omer mi-Tzion michlal yofi Elohim hofia,
ממנו מכלל
יפיו של עולם. mimenu michlal yofyo shel olam. Okay so God called
the world into being and the sun and anyway it all comes
from ציון. Tzion. So again this idea that even you know that
everything sort of derives from a I would say you know I
would argue a physical manifestation of a spiritual essence which is ציון
Tzion you know is very different than a more naturalistic type of
an explanation, you know earth things come from earth and heaven things
come from heaven and you know it sort of is a allows
for there to be sort of nature to have its own due
you know and as opposed to sort of seeing everything as as
I would sort of see it as some type of an emanation
from a from a spiritual essence. That's what I sort of see
as the fundamental difference here. I don't know if I could do
much more with that גמרא. Gemara, But
anyway. All right let's take a look now as the גמרא Gemara
continues. נטל דמה ממי שהיה ממרס בו. Natal dama mi-mi she-hayah memares
bo. Now we get back to the עבודה. He he took the
blood from the one who was who was stirring it. And he
says he would sprinkle now let's read the language of the משנה.
Mishnah. The משנה Mishnah says he took the blood he went back
he went into the קדש הקדשים, Kodesh HaKodashim, he stood where he
stood and he said והזה ממנו אחת למעלה ושבע למטה, ve-hizah mimenu
achat le-ma'alah ve-sheva le-matah,
one up and seven down. We'll talk about what that means in
a minute. ולא היה מתכוין להזות לא למעלה ולא למטה. Ve-lo hayah
mitkavein lehazot lo le-ma'alah ve-lo le-matah. He didn't intend to sprinkle up
and down. So then what does it mean he sprinkles up and
down? אלא כמצליף. Ela kematzlif. He was like a מצליף. matzlif. But
what does this all mean? So let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara מאי כמצליף? Mai kematzlif? What does that mean? מחוי רב
יהודה, Machvi Rav Yehudah, רב יהודה Rav Yehudah demonstrated כמנגדא, ke-minagda, like
somebody giving lashes. Now what does that mean? So it it might
mean that the that the movement was more in the in the
arm than in the wrist, right? You could imagine a whole thing
that was is very much about the wrist, right? As opposed to
like if you give lashes, I mean I assume you could give
lashes with your wrist but it wouldn't be as effective as if
you use your arm. So could mean it has more to do
with arm movement. Also one question is is that like... Also one
question is how much do you wait till you're finished with the
movement to release the blow? Like you do the lashes, it's like
when you get down is when you release it. So if we
imagine down, it's
only when your arm is sort of all the way down do
you sprinkle. Another possibility also that תוספות one place seems to indicate,
we'll see more in a minute as we try to get clarity
about what was done, is that it also means that it was
like רש"י Rashi says, כמטה ברצועה שמתחיל מן הכתפיים ומכה והולך למטה.
kematah baretzuah shemachil min haksafayim u’maka veholech lematah.
רש"י Rashi says it specifically means that you were trying to sort
of almost do them in a line, you first hit in the
shoulders if you're giving lashes and then lower and lower so you're
trying to make them hit like in a line going sequentially. תוספות
I believe in זבחים Zevachim indicates that more the opposite, if I
remember correctly, that it was more like when you give... you're not
exactly trying to make it hit any specific part. It's connecting to
the משנה Mishna that says לא היה מתכוון לא למטה ולא למעלה.
Lo hayah miskavein lo lematah velo lemala. You're not sort of trying
to specifically
aim it at a particular point. So it's a little unclear what
exactly this is trying to say. Again, I think the simple sense
one hand might be it's more in the arm than in the
wrist, and also for רש"י Rashi it also means you were trying
to get them to line up, but it's possible that it might
mean the opposite. Okay.
מחוי machvei means he demonstrated physically or he said?
He demonstrated. מחוי machvei always means he demonstrated, כחויה. kechavayah. Yes,
to express, but מחוי machvei means he demonstrated, yeah. Okay. So the
מר Mar says תנא. tana. Now we're going to get a little
bit more clarity. כשהוא מזה אינו מזה על הכפורת אלא כנגד עוביה
של הכפורת. kshehu mazeh eino mazeh al hakaporeth ela keneged ovyah shel
hakaporeth.
Now as the תורה Torah says, what does the תורה Torah say
about how he does the sprinkling? Right, so there's פסוקים psukim by
the פר, par, there's פסוקים psukim by the שעיר. sair. So the
פסוקים psukim say,
goes like this: ולקח מדם הפר והזה
באצבעו על פני הכפרת קדמה, velakach
midam hapar vehizah
be’etzbao al pnei hakaporeth kedmah, on
the face of the כפורת kaporeth eastward, ולפני
הכפורת יזה שבע פעמים מן הדם באצבעו velifnei hakaporeth yazeh sheva peamim
min hadam be’etzbao and in front he should sprinkle seven
times. So if you said on the face eastward, well
first of all what's eastward? So if this is the
כפורת kaporeth and the כהן גדול kohen gadol is entering in this
way, this is East, this is West. So this thing keeps on
dying on me.
Okay.
So this is East and this is West, so eastward you would
think means על פני הכפורת al pnei hakaporeth means exactly
if this is the thing on top of the ark. If
this is the ark and this is the כפורת kaporeth on top
of the ark, it's a lid, and you're coming in here from
the East, facing westward, but על פני הכפורת קדמה al pnei hakaporeth
kedmah the face of it eastward probably means this thickness of the
lid facing out and then לפני הכפורת lifnei hakaporeth means you don't
try to hit on the כפורת, kaporeth, you just do it in
front of. So the simple sense of the פסוקים psukim is that
one sprinkle in the above hit here and the others for maybe
fall on the ground or whatever are done in front of it
but not to hit here. Okay. So let's take a look though
at the גמרא, Gemara it says none of it actually hits the
כפורת. kaporeth. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. So it says
like this, אמר קרא, amar kra, so it says like this, מנא
הני מילי mana hanei mili אמר רב אחא בר יעקב. amar Rav
Acha bar Yaakov. I'm sorry, that's תנא, tana, כשהוא מזה אינו מזה
על הכפורת אלא כנגד עוביה של הכפורת. kshehu mazeh eino mazeh al
hakaporeth ela keneged ovyah shel hakaporeth.
Not on it, which seems to also be excluding the top of
it, but rather opposite the thickness of it. כנגד עוביה, keneged ovyah,
not to hit the thickness of it which is what we just
said but opposite the thickness of it. כשהוא מזה למעלה, kshehu mazeh
lemala,
now when he's doing it above, מצדד ידו למטה, mitzadeid yado lematah,
he has his hand facing below. כשהוא מזה למטה, kshehu mazeh lematah,
when he does it below, מצדד ידו למעלה, mitzadeid yado lemala, he
has his hand facing above. What does this mean? So there's a
debate between רש"י Rashi and רבינו חננאל. Rabbeinu Chananel. רש"י Rashi says
מצדד ידו למטה mitzadeid yado lematah means the back of his hand.
So רש"י Rashi says when he's doing it above, he has his
hand like this and he goes like that which would sort of
get it into his face like maybe he goes like that or
he starts like that and he goes like that. Exactly. And when
he does it below, he sort of goes like this, which is
also a little uncomfortable. רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel says the opposite, it
means the palm of his hand so that when he goes above,
the palm of his hand is below so he goes like that
which is an easy movement and when he goes down, the palm
of his hand is like this and he goes down actually so
in one it's a flicking up. Wait did I do that right?
No.
Let's do that again. Either way it looks very comfortable. Right.
When he does above, okay, he says the palm of his hand
is down so he sticks his finger in the blood and he
goes like that and the blood goes up. Right, like that. When
he does below, now you could have done below the same thing
but anyway he says when you do below you have your palm
of your hand facing up and yes that's a little bit harder.
Yeah, it's a lot harder.
Anyway, so anyway but that's what he says. Okay. And what's important
for him is he also says because I always have this confusion
what's above what's below where's he going so רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel
makes it very clear. That above means actually you're throwing the blood
up and down means again both would be easier if your palm
was facing down I think, but below means that your blood is
facing is facing down. Okay. So that's how he reads it. And
he says, what?
It's nothing to do with מכה. makah.
It's nothing to do with, yeah, the מכה makah is not clear.
He says the מכה makah he just says, yeah,
he does it as
a מכה makah like that. Right, right. But he says אינו מכה
עד שיורד, eino makah ad sheyored, so he might mean you go
like that, you know, you wait till you get down, you start
high and you go like
that, you know, as opposed and when you go up, you know,
you go like that or something, I don't know, or like that.
Anyway. Okay. So I'm trying I'm doing the best I can here.
But anyway, so הגמרא ha-Gemara says like this.
Okay. So now if you take a look, רבנו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel
is actually interesting where it goes. He says like this, one minute.
One minute. Yeah,
if you take a look at where רבנו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel begins,
it's like right after the bottom of the last line of תוספות
where it says כיצד כשמזה למעלה מצדד ידו למטה פירוש נותן כף
ידו למטה ואצבעותיו כלפי מעלה ומזה וזו שהיא מזה עולה למעלה מן
הכפורת. keitzad keshemaze l'maala m'tzaded yado l'mata peirush noten kaff yado l'mata
v'etzbe'otav klapei maala u'maze v'zo shehi maze olah l'maala min ha-kaporet.
So when it goes up, what it means למעלה, l'maala, the one
that's up, is goes higher than the כפורת, kaporet, כנגד הכפורת מחוץ
הכפורת, k'neged ha-kaporet m'chutz ha-kaporet,
opposite it but not touching it, like you know outside of it,
so it's in front of the כפורת kaporet but going up higher
than it. וחוזר ונופל למטה בקרקע v'chozer v'nofel l'mata bakarka and then
it falls back down. וכשהוא מזה למטה, u'keshehu maze l'mata,
when he does the ones that are seven below, מצדד ידו למעלה
כלומר כף יד למעלה ואצבעותיו למטה ומזה כנגד עוביה של כפורת, m'tzaded
yado l'maala klomar kaff yad l'maala v'etzbe'otav l'mata u'maze k'neged ovyah shel
kaporet, שהיא מצחה. shehi mitzcha.
He has this whole ירושלמי Yerushalmi they call the thickness of it
its forehead because it has a פנים, panim, it has a forehead.
והיא טפחה, v'hi tipcha, כדחזינן k'd'chazinan on ארון aron whatever. וזו שמזה
יורדת ונופלת בקרקע מחוץ של ארון כנגדו. v'zo shemaze yoredet v'nofelet bakarka
m'chutz shel aron k'negdo. Okay.
So anyway, one starts over here and goes high above it, and
the other maybe starts at the thickness of the כפורת kaporet and
goes down from the thickness. So one rises up in front. So
the way he reads it is, you know, על הכפורת al ha-kaporet
somehow means in the presence of the כפורת kaporet but it goes
up in front and לפני lifnei somehow means starts in front of
it and goes down. So הגמרא ha-Gemara is now going to figure
out where you get this idea of up and down, when you
have it in this simple sense of the verse, which means one
is on and the seven are not on. So let's take a
look. מנא הני מילי? mina hanei milei? אמר רב אחא בר יעקב
אמר רב חסדא, amar Rav Acha bar Yaakov amar Rav Chisda, אמר
קרא, amar kra, the verse says, והזה אותו על הכפורת ולפני הכפורת.
v'hizah oto al ha-kaporet v'lifnei ha-kaporet. לא יאמר למטה בשעיר. lo yomar
l'mata b'sa'ir.
Now here's the issue. The תורה Torah says by the פר par
the following: ולקח מדם הפר והזה באצבעו על פני הכפורת קדמה.
v'lakach midam ha-par v'hizah b'etzba'o
al pnei ha-kaporet kedma. Okay, so the one that's על פני al
pnei just says do it,
it doesn't say how many. ולפני הכפורת יזה שבע פעמים מן הדם
באצבעו, v'lifnei ha-kaporet yazeh sheva pe'amim min ha-dam b'etzba'o, and in front
seven times. Now when it gets to the שעיר, sa'ir, it says
like this: ועשה את דמו כאשר עשה לדם הפר והזה אותו על
הכפורת ולפני הכפורת. v'asah et damo ka'asher asah l'dam ha-par v'hizah oto
al ha-kaporet v'lifnei ha-kaporet. Do it on the כפורת kaporet and in
front of the כפורת. kaporet.
So it already says do it like you did to the דם
הפר, dam ha-par, but then it repeats even again, והזה אותו על
הכפורת ולפני הכפורת. v'hizah oto al ha-kaporet v'lifnei ha-kaporet.
So the question is why do they have to repeat that once
you said do it like you did with the פר? par? Let's
take a look. לא יאמר למטה בשעיר, lo yomar l'mata b'sa'ir,
don't tell me explicitly do it below, which we're assuming means below,
right, ולפני הכפורת v'lifnei ha-kaporet by the שעיר. sa'ir. דלא צריך, d'lo
tzarich, you don't need to tell it to me, דגמר ממטה דפר.
d'gamar mi-mata d'par. You already said do it like you did with
the ox. At the ox it said you do it seven times.
למה נאמר? lama ne'emar? So why does it say do it? לאקושי
על ולפני, l'akushei al v'lifnei,
to connect where it says 'on' to where it says 'in the
presence of'. מה לפני דלאו על אף על דלאו
על. mah lifnei d'lav al af al d'lav al. The same way
'in front of' doesn't mean 'on', 'on' doesn't mean 'on'. Okay, 'on'
means 'in front of'. So basically what you've got is,
right,
the תורה Torah says by the שעיר, sa'ir,
it says by the פר, par, it says והזה אותו על הכפורת,
v'hizah oto al ha-kaporet, plus ולפני הכפורת יזה שבע פעמים. v'lifnei ha-kaporet
yazeh sheva pe'amim.
That's what it says by the פר. par. And by the שעיר
sa'ir it says כאשר עשה לדם הפר. ka'asher asah l'dam ha-par.
So we already know that you do the same. And then it
repeats and says והזה אותו על הכפורת ולפני הכפורת. v'hizah oto al
ha-kaporet v'lifnei ha-kaporet. Okay.
So the על al here literally means 'on', this is 'in front
of', the על al and the לפני, lifnei, and we're going to
translate this to be one above and seven below. One above and
seven below. The question is why after it said כאשר עשה לדם
הפר ka'asher asa l'dam hapar does it have to repeat this? Don't
say ולמטה ולפני הכפורת v'lematah v'lifnei hakaporeth and I would have learned
it from the פר. par. Why does it say it? The only
reason to say it is to tell me to connect the first
half, the על al to the לפני, lifnei, and the same way
לפני lifnei obviously doesn't mean on, so על al doesn't mean on,
okay? So therefore it's only coming here to show you that the
על al. here doesn't literally mean on.
It could have been the other way.
It could have been the same way על al means on, לפני
lifnei means on.
It could have been, right.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara will take a look at it. Let's
take a look. Okay. למה יאמר למעלה, Lama yomar l'malah, okay, הגמרא
בבית הבחירה, haGemara b'veit habechira, למה נאמר לקושי על לפני מה לפני
דלאו על אף על דלאו על. Lama ne'emar l'kushi al lifnei mah
lifnei d'lav al af al d'lav al. Okay, אדרבה adrava says the
גמרא Gemara the opposite. לא יאמר, Lo yomar, don't say למעלה בפר,
l'malah b'par, דלא צריך. d'lo tzarich.
Once these are connected and here it says והזה אותו על הכפורת,
v'hizah oto al hakaporeth, why does it have to say that this
is? Now meaning there's no question
why this is needed. This is why this is needed because here
it says seven times and here it doesn't. So if you want
to say seven times by the שעיר, se'ir, you have to learn
it from here. We know why this is needed, okay? But we
don't know, I'm sorry I might have said it wrong a second
ago, we know why this is needed. This is needed to tell
me seven times. We don't know why this is needed because, did
I, am I making a mistake again? Wait one minute.
למה נאמר, Lama ne'emar, hold on let me just take a look.
לא יאמר למטה בשעיר, Lo yomar l'matah b'se'ir, no
no no, okay,
I'm sorry, okay,
anyway, this says seven times, so you need to link the שעיר
se'ir to the פר par to learn out seven times because it
says seven times. The גמרא's Gemara point before was you don't need
to say it explicitly here because it already said כאשר עשה. ka'asher
asa. But you need to link the שעיר se'ir to the פר
par in order to learn out the seven times, okay? But why
do you need, says the גמרא, Gemara to say once you've linked
the פר par and the שעיר, se'ir, why do you need it
to say והזה אותו על הכפורת v'hizah oto al hakaporeth by the
פר? par? Once they're being linked, say it by the שעיר se'ir
and you can retrospectively figure out by the פר. par.
All right, we know, and that's the simple answer, but the גמרא's
Gemara question is once
they're being linked, you can't say you don't need this by the
פר par because this says seven times and it doesn't say it
here. But you could say you don't need this and you could
have learned it out from the שעיר. se'ir. So let's take a
look what the answer is.
Someone was asking why didn't you just take out all the פר
par part by the שעיר? se'ir?
Well we'll get to that, we'll get to that, we'll get to
that. Okay let's take a look. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says,
okay, אדרבה, adrava, לא יאמר למעלה בפר, lo yomar l'malah b'par,
don't say the one above by the פר, par, דלא צריך דגמרי
ממעלה דשעיר, d'lo tzarich d'gamri mimalah d'se'ir, once they're being linked you
can learn out from the שעיר. se'ir. למה נאמר, Lama ne'emar, why
was it said? לקושי, L'kushi, to connect לפני לאל, lifnei l'al, the
opposite of what you were saying before. The idea of in presence
of, of in front of, to the על. al מה על על
ממש אף לפני על ממש. Mah al al mamash af lifnei al
mamash.
So in the same way על al means on, לפני lifnei means
on. So the assumption is that what's extra here is, you know
what's extra is learning out from, is the one that's, that's teaching
you, you know, what it really means. So when we said the
לפני lifnei was extra because you could have learned it out from
the link, the לפני lifnei is teaching you that it really means
in front of and not on, and it teaches you that the
על al means in front of. So the גמרא Gemara says do
the opposite, say the על al. here is extra because you could
have learned it out this way, and the על al, is teaching
you what it all really means and it all really means on
and even the לפני lifnei means on. So maybe everything has to
be on, okay? So what?
No two different.
All right let's not ask questions, let's just finish this גמרא gemara
out. Okay, so the גמרא gemara says like this,
okay, so the גמרא Gemara says היי מאי, hai mai, what type
of a question is that? So,
היי מאי, hai mai, what type of a question is that?
אי אמרת בשלמא למטה דשעיר לקושי למעלה
דפר, Ei amart b'shlama l'matah d'se'ir l'kushi l'malah d'par, if you said
that it was, that the purpose of saying the below by the
שעיר se'ir was to teach you that idea that it didn't literally
mean on, so למעלה דפר מיבעי ליה, l'malah d'par miba'ei leh, then
you understand also why you needed to tell me the above by
the cow. לכדתני דבי רבי אליעזר בן יעקב, Lichdetanya d'bei Rabbi Eliezer
ben Yaakov, דתני דבי רבי אליעזר בן יעקב, d'tanya d'bei Rabbi Eliezer
ben Yaakov, I'll just read this on plain, על פני הכפורת קדמה
זה בני אב כל מקום שנאמר פני אינו אלא קדים. al pnei
hakaporeth kedmah zeh b'nei av kol makom she'ne'emar pnei eino ela kadim.
When it says על פני הכפורת קדמה, al pnei hakaporeth kedmah, it
means teaches you that the face always means the east. So meaning
what we're saying is we have two things that are considered to
be extra, okay? Once this פסוק pasuk. links them, links the two
of them, so they're equal, so then there's certain פסוקים pesukim that
are extra. This is extra, right, because this could have been just
achieved by the link, and this is considered to be extra because
that could have been achieved by the link. Now why do you
say that even this was extra, okay? So the גמרא Gemara somehow
assumes that the fact that it says by the שעיר, se'ir, you
know, והזה אותו על הכפורת v'hizah oto al hakaporeth is, I don't
know why it's
assumed, one
minute. It says, what does it say? It says וזה באצבעו—oh v'hizah
b'etzba'o no, here's the difference. Here it says והזה באצבעו v'hizah b'etzba'o
and here it says אותו על הכפורת. oto al hakaporeth. So from
אותו oto we learn out it means one. And here it does
not say אותו. oto.
It just says והזה. v'hizah.
Okay, it
doesn't say how many times. אותו Oto is singular.
אותו Oto is singular, right. So basically, although this whole thing isn't
working, we'll have to do this another time. So anyway, okay, so
I think this is getting a little bit confusing. Let's try this
again, okay? So by the פר, par, it says והזה על, v'hizah
al,
and we don't know how—והזה על הכפורת, v'hizah al hakaporeth,
we don't know how many times. And then it says ולפני הכפורת
יזה שבע פעמים, v'lifnei hakaporeth yazeh sheva pe'amim, okay,
seven. But we don't know how many times—okay, by the שעיר, se'ir,
it says, maybe it should be—והזה אותו, v'hizah oto, which means one,
and then it says—no, it says by the שעיר, se'ir, והביא את
דמו, v'hevi et damo, yeah, והזה
אותו,
v'hizah
oto, ולפני
הכפורת.
v'lifnei hakaporeth.
Okay, והזה אותו על הכפורת ולפני
הכפורת.
v'hizah oto
al
hakaporeth v'lifnei hakaporeth.
Okay,
so here, what we learn out—I need another color—here we learn out
the seven, here we learn out the one, okay. The other stuff
isn't clear, and the תורה Torah says כאשר עשה, ka'asher asah, which
means they're equal, כאשר עשה. ka'asher asah.
So that means that they're equal, okay. So if they're equal, it
says we don't need—we need this to tell me the one, we
need this to tell me the seven, we don't need this and
we don't need that. Okay, that's what we don't need. So the
גמרא Gemara says, the fact that this is extra tells me that
what we really need is—is לפני. lifnei. We don't need that anything
is actually על. al. That's what that being extra teaches. We'll tell
in a minute what this being extra means. That's the first approach,
that the לפני lifnei tells me that we don't need על, al
okay, not על. al. And that's what we learn out by that
extra. Right. But then it tells me that the אותו oto and
the other—the על al, means, okay, means not על. al, It teaches
me that everything means מלפני. mi'lifnei. The גמרא Gemara challenges it and
says, no, let's focus on the fact that this is extra, and
this means על, al. and this tells me that everything means על,
al even the לפני lifnei means על. al? So which one do
you start with? You start with this telling me not על al,
or this telling me yes על? al, And the גמרא says, I
understand if we start with this not על, al, I'd have something
to do with this פסוק. pasuk With this I can teach me
something from this extra part. But if I start with this to
teach me that everything means על, al, I have nothing to do
with that. And therefore since this other way explains how I can
use everything, that's the right way to look at it. We'll tell
in a minute what it means. This means not על, al. and
this tells me something else. What does this tell me something else?
Because it says על פני הכפורת קדמה, al pnei hakaporeth kedmah, and
it tells me a general principle that פנים panim equals קדם, kedem,
which is relevant in other places. So I have a use for
this פסוק pasuk, and I have a use for this, but if
you said that this is coming to teach me that it all
literally means על, al. then that's completely superfluous. So that can't be
what's going on.
How does the application of בנין אב binyan av work? It simply
asserts that this is the אב?
av? Yeah, yeah, if in one place it's taken for granted, then
that's assumed to be a rule.
We're going to say—make explicit that this is the אב av for
every place else.
Exactly. Okay. Alright,
בסיעתא דשמיא—yeah, B'syata d'shmaya
I finally figured out how to do it better graphically. Alright, so
the גמרא says like this. Okay. Okay, says הי מאי? אי אמרת
בשלמא למטה דשעיר לאקושי למעלה דפר—to Hai mai? Ei amart bishlama l'mata
d'se'ir l'akushei l'ma'ala d'par the below
by the שעיר se'ir the seven, it's telling me that everything means
in front of and not על. al למעלה דפר מיבעי ליה, L'ma'ala
d'par miba'ei leh, so the first thing by the פר par that's
also extra, מיבעי ליה, miba'ei leh, that has a purpose, לכדתני דבי
רבי אליעזר בן יעקב. le'khid'tanei d'bei Rabbi Eliezer ben Ya'akov. דתני דבי
רבי אליעזר בן יעקב: על פני הכפורת קדמה—זה בנה אב כל מקום
שנאמר פני אינו אלא קדים.
D'tanei d'bei Rabbi Eliezer ben Ya'akov: Al pnei hakaporeth kedmah—zeh banah av,
kol makom
shene'emar panim eino ela kadim. אלא אי אמרת למעלה דפר לאקושי, Ela
ei amart l'ma'ala d'par l'akushei, but if we focus on the—the first
one of the פר par as the extra, and that that's coming
to teach me the idea that it always means—that it means literally
על. al. So למטה דשעיר למה לי אתא? l'mata d'se'ir lamah li
ata? So what's the purpose of telling me the below by the
שעיר, se'ir, which I could have figured out from the equation? So
therefore since this way explains all the extra parts of the פסוק,
pasuk, that's the way to learn it. And the bottom line is
because it says לפני lifnei and that's considered to be extra, that
tells me even the על means לפני lifnei and nothing literally means
על. It all means in front of. And there's one above and
seven below. What exactly that means, again according to רבינו חננאל, Rabbeinu
Chananel, it means that it would be—that it means that it's—that it's
done—that one literally is—is thrown upward and seven are thrown downward. By
the way, I'm now remembering that one of the מפרשים mefarshim explains,
actually this explains רבינו חננאל, Rabbeinu Chananel, why you would do the
seven downward this way, even though it's physically harder, is because if
you do it this way apparently the blood will get into your
sleeve or
something.
Everything went on the floor.
Everything went on
the
floor.
Did anyone ever go into the קודש קדשים Kodesh Kodashim except the
כהן גדול on יום כיפור? Yom Kippur No maintenance guy?
No maintenance people did. We mentioned that before, yeah.
So they went in and cleaned up during the year?
They did. Yeah, with... I don't know if they cleaned up the
blood, yeah, but yeah. They did. Okay.
They went to the side of
the...
he's
standing in front of the ארון aron, right now. I mean...
but it doesn't hit because he's standing far enough away or he's
standing off to the side. No, it's like this. There's a
פרוכת parochet would be at my back, this would be the stone
or this would be the ארון, aron. and I'd be between the
פרוכת parochet and the ארון. aron. And I'm either going up or
going down and it's all going right in front of the ארון.
aron, Okay. Did they ever touch the floor or were they allowed
to? Yeah, yeah.
Yeah,
the כפורת. kapporet.
Yeah, oh you said...
oh כפורת kapporet I think I translated as... okay, I'm sorry, I
misheard you. But yeah, I'm sorry, so what are you asking?
Is there some distance or off to the side?
I said so it won't hit as it goes... well he's not
throwing it at it. He's right in front of it and it's
going either straight up in front or straight down in front. That's
how I understand. All right. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. והזה אותו על
הכפורת ולפני הכפורת. Vehizah oto al hakapporet velifnei hakapporet. למדנו כמה למעלה
בשעיר אחת, למטה בשעיר איני יודע. Lamadnu kamah lema'lah basair achat, lema'tah
basair eini yodea.
So this is what I said before. By the שעיר sair it
says אותו, oto, that's one above. I don't know how many below.
כמה כמה הריני דן. Kamah kamah hareni dan. So I can learn
it out. נאמרו דמים למטה בפר ונאמרו דמים למטה בשעיר. Ne'emru damim
lema'tah bapar vene'emru damim lema'tah basair. It says by the פר par
how many below, seven, and it says by the שעיר sair below.
מה למטה בפר שבע אף למטה בשעיר שבע. Mah lema'tah bapar sheva
af lema'tah basair sheva. So the below is seven, so the below
is seven. או כלך לדרך זו. O kelach lederech zu. Or go
this opposite way. נאמרו דמים למעלה בשעיר ונאמרו דמים למטה בשעיר. Ne'emru
damim lema'lah basair vene'emru damim lema'tah basair. It says above and it
says below by the goat. מה למעלה בשעיר אחת אף למטה בשעיר
אחת. Mah lema'lah basair achat af lema'tah basair achat. Maybe I should
say that the below is not similar to the פר, par, it's
similar to what you told me to do the above by the
goat, which is one. נראה למי דומה. Nireh lemi domeh. Let's see
which is more comparable. דנין מטה ממטה ואין דנין מטה ממעלה. Danin
matah mimmatah ve'ein danin matah mimma'lah. Let's learn below from below and
not below from above, which it says here again, ignoring the equation
sign, which is what we're going to get to. If you didn't
have the equation sign and it just says והזה אותו על הכפורת
ולפני הכפורת, Vehizah oto al hakapporet velifnei hakapporet, what would you have
said? Would you have said על הכפורת ולפני הכפורת al hakapporet velifnei
hakapporet means they're both the same and אותו oto means one, so
one above and seven below? Or would you say no, it's in
parallel to the פר, par, and the same way this is seven
below, this is seven below? So would you have learned it out
from above to below, one and one, or would you have learned
it out by the parallel to the פר? par? What would I
have done without the equation sign? So it says נראה למי דומה.
Nireh lemi domeh. Let's see which it's more comparable to. דנין מטה
ממטה. Danin matah mimmatah. Let's learn below from below, seven by the
פר, par, פר שעיר. par sair. ואין דנין מטה ממעלה. Ve'ein danin
matah mimma'lah.
Don't do the below from the above. מה שאתה אומר אדרבה. Mah
she'atah omer adarabbah. The opposite. דנין גופא מגופא ואין דנין גופא מעלמא.
Danin gufa migufa ve'ein danin gufa me'alma. Let's learn it from itself.
Since its own blood was one above, it should be one below,
and don't learn it from somewhere else. תלמוד לומר ועשה את דמו
כאשר עשה לדם הפר. Talmud lomar ve'asah et damo ka'asher asah ledam
hapar. You have an equation sign. שאין תלמוד לומר כאשר עשה. She'ein
talmud lomar ka'asher asah. It doesn't have to say as you did.
ומה תלמוד לומר כאשר עשה? Umah talmud lomar ka'asher asah?
So what's the emphasis of equating them? שיהיו כל עשיותיו שוות. Sheyihyu
kol asiyotav shavot. To make them equal. כשם שלמטה בפר שבע כך
למטה בשעיר שבע. Keshem shelema'tah bapar sheva kach lema'tah basair sheva. Okay,
so seven below by the פר, par, seven below by the שעיר.
sair. Fine. למדנו כמה למטה בפר Lamadnu kamah lema'tah bapar now we
know how much is below by the ox ובשעיר שבע. uvasair sheva.
Below by the ox and the goat are seven. למעלה בפר איני
יודע. Lema'lah bapar eini yodea. Now we get back to the other
thing we don't know if it weren't for the equal sign. How
much do you do above by the ox? כמה הריני דן. Kamah
hareni dan. נאמרו דמים למעלה בשעיר ונאמרו דמים למעלה בפר. Ne'emru damim
lema'lah basair vene'emru damim lema'lah bapar.
So we know how much is above by the goat, one, and
we know that you do above by the ox. מה למעלה בשעיר
אחת אף למעלה בפר אחת. Mah lema'lah basair achat af lema'lah bapar
achat. So let's say the one above by the goat, parallel to
it one above by the cow... by the ox. Okay. או כלך
לדרך זו. O kelach lederech zu. Go this way. נאמרו דמים למטה
בפר ונאמרו דמים למעלה בפר. Ne'emru damim lema'tah bapar vene'emru damim lema'lah
bapar. Let's learn above from below. מה למטה בפר שבע אף למעלה
בפר שבע. Mah lema'tah bapar sheva af lema'lah bapar sheva.
So the same point except here looking at this side. It says
והזה אותו על הכפורת ולפני הכפורת שבע פעמים. Vehizah oto al hakapporet
velifnei hakapporet sheva pe'amim.
So how many would I do על הכפורת? al hakapporet? Maybe I
should say since it says לפני שבע פעמים, lifnei sheva pe'amim, here
I should do... should do שבע פעמים. sheva pe'amim. So let me
learn the פר par itself above from below or would I learn
it by parallel. Since by the שעיר sair it's one above, here
too it's one above. Which would I learn? Would I learn it
from itself or would I learn it by parallel to the שעיר
sair if I didn't have the equal sign? You could have gone
either way. Let's just finish this. Okay. נראה למי דומה. Nireh lemi
domeh. Which is it more comparable to? דנין מעלה ממעלה. Danin ma'alah
mimma'lah. Let's learn above from above ואין דנין מעלה ממטה. ve'ein danin
ma'alah mimmatah. Not above from below. So let's learn the ox from
the שעיר. sair. One above by the שעיר, sair, one above by
the ox. אדרבה. Adarabbah. The opposite. דנין גופא מגופא. Danin gufa migufa.
Let's learn the ox from itself. And since below it's seven, above
it should be seven, ואין דני גופו מעלמא, v'ein dani gufo me'alma,
and not from
elsewhere. ומה תלמוד לומר כאשר עשה, u'ma talmud lomar ka'asher asa, what's
the whole point of
emphasis of the equation? ומה תלמוד לומר כאשר עשה, u'ma talmud lomar
ka'asher asa, שיהיו כל העשיות שוות, she'yehyu kol ha'asiyos shavos, the same
way we've already learned out that the equation tells us seven below
by the goat, by what we learned it from the ox, if
that's one thing, כשם שלמטה בפר שבע כך למטה בשעיר שבע, keshem
she'lemata bapar sheva kach lemata ba'se'ir sheva, the same way above by
the goat is one, וכשם שלמעלה בשעיר אחת כך למעלה בפר אחת,
u'keshem she'lema'ala ba'se'ir achas kach lema'ala bapar achas, above by the cow
ox is one.
So the need for the equation sign, whereas if I just had
these individually, I would have had seven here and one here and
I wouldn't have known what to do with this. Should I have
said one one?
Or should I have said by parallel seven seven? Same here, should
I have said seven seven up here, should I have learned it
out from here? I wouldn't have known if it wasn't for the
equal signs. The equal sign tells me exactly to learn across, above
from above and below from below, and then it makes this extra
and this extra, and that's what we said, is that then I
can learn the idea that it doesn't literally mean on, it means
in front of. Okay. Clear?
Yeah, I just want to keep the choreography straight. He's got two
bowls of blood.
He's only got one so far, we're not up to the second
one. But there's two separate bowls.
Yeah, he hasn't mixed them together yet.
He hasn't even gotten to the—he hasn't even shechted the goat yet.
We haven't got to that, we're just looking at the פסוקים, psukim,
okay. I'm serious. He's only done—okay, fine, I'm
trying to keep it straight.
All right. So let's get to that. Okay. תנו רבנן אחת אחת
ואחת אחת ושתיים אחת ושלוש אחת וארבע אחת וחמש אחת ושש אחת
ושבע. tanu rabanan achas achas v'achas achas u'shtayim achas v'shalosh achas v'arba
achas v'chamesh achas v'shesh achas v'sheva. So now we're still with the
ox and now we got the idea one above and seven below,
let's say one flick up, seven flicks down. It's not intended to
hit the ארון, and now we talk about the counting. תנו רבנן
אחת אחת ואחת אחת ושתיים אחת ושלוש אחת וארבע אחת וחמש אחת
ושש אחת ושבע, tanu rabanan achas achas v'achas achas u'shtayim achas v'shalosh
achas v'arba achas v'chamesh achas v'shesh achas v'sheva, דברי רבי מאיר. divrei
rabbi meir. רבי יהודה אומר אחת אחת ואחת שתיים ואחת שלוש ואחת
ארבע ואחת חמש ואחת שש ואחת שבע ואחת. rabbi yehuda omer achas
achas v'achas shtayim v'achas shalosh v'achas arba v'achas chamesh v'achas shesh v'achas
sheva v'achas. Okay,
so do you first say the one and seven or seven and
one? So the גמרא says ולא פליגי, v'lo pligi,
they don't really disagree. מר כי אתריה ומר כי אתריה, mar k'asrei
u'mar k'asrei, each one goes according to his place. Meaning what? What
the כהן גדול did in his place? No, but what it means
is—no it means is how would you count? רש"י rashi says do
you count when you're sort of saying you know do you say
twenty-one or one and twenty? Right, it's just a count. Right,
exactly, exactly. So he says the same here, you know do you
sort of start with what you've already done, one and one, one
and two, like twenty-one, twenty-two, or do you say two and one,
three and one, four and one, go back to what you've done
before. All right, so that's the debate of how you would do
it. Okay. דכולי עלמא מיהת, d'kulei alma me'has, everybody agrees on the
last הזאה ראשונה צריכה מנין עם כל אחת ואחת, haza'a rishona tzricha
minyan im kol achas v'achas, that you have to continue to count
the first one even though you're now on the second—I mean you
could have asked everybody said you have to count the seven, what
does it even say you have to count the seven? Okay, עם
כל אחת ואחת. im kol achas v'achas. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? What's
the reason? רבי אלעזר אומר שלא יטעה בהזאות, rabbi elazar omer she'lo
yiteh b'haza'os, you shouldn't get confused. Now what's getting confused? So I
would say getting confused is that you count the first one as
one of the seven, right, and you sort of get off. One,
two—or you know, wait, am I counting the first one, not counting
the first? רש"י rashi says something different, which is if you look
at רש"י, rashi, the רש"י rashi
says שלא יטעה, she'lo yiteh, ten lines before the bottom or twelve
lines, שיהא לו שהות בינתיים לתת לבו למנין שלא יטעה. she'yehei lo
sehus beintayim latet libo l'minyan she'lo yiteh. So רש"י rashi sounds like
it's just to slow you down when you say one, one and
one, one and two, one and three, you're just being more, you
know, you're just being more deliberate so that you're slowed down. You
don't get sort of caught up, one, two, three, whatever. So it
doesn't—but I would have thought like I said that it's just so
you don't accidentally count the first one as one of the seven.
רש"י rashi doesn't seem to be saying that. Okay, that's one explanation.
Then you get eight, you're getting eight there, you're not getting seven.
Right, right, but if I say
one and then I start with the others, one, two, three, four,
I might actually have counted the first one as part of those.
So that's why I thought it was separate, but anyway רש"י rashi
says it's just to slow you down. Okay.
רבי יוחנן אמר קרא ולפני הכפורת יזה שבע פעמים, rabbi yochanan amar
kra v'lifnei ha'kapores yazeh sheva pe'amim, in front of the כפורת kapores
he shall יזה yazeh seven times. שאין תלמוד לומר יזה, she'ein talmud
lomar yazeh, it just could have said in front of the כפורת,
kapores, the verb is understood. ומה תלמוד לומר יזה? u'ma talmud lomar
yazeh? Why does it repeat the verb? ללמד על הזאה ראשונה שצריכה
מנין עם כל אחת ואחת. l'lamed al haza'a rishona she'tzricha minyan im
kol achas v'achas. The repetition of the verb יזה yazeh when it
gets to the seven is telling you take that original הזאה haza'a
and it should continue through for these seven הזאות. haza'os. It should
continue to be counted. Okay. So מאי בינייהו? mai beina'ihu? What's the
difference? What would be different? איכא בינייהו דלא מנה ולא טעה. ika
beina'ihu d'lo mana v'lo ta'ah. You didn't do the counting and you
didn't make a mistake. According to the first one it was only
a secondary concern, so you didn't count fine, it's still good. According
to רבי יוחנן rabbi yochanan no, you literally have—it's the פסוק, you
gotta do it. Which is quite fascinating, I mean even the counting
of the seven isn't—maybe the גמרא understands that the word שבע sheva
implicitly suggests that there will be a counting that's being done, not
just a mental counting.
I don't know, a number suggests it's being counted.
And that somehow that there's actually this requirement to include them. So
it would be interesting to speculate on what is the symbolism of
including the one with the seven. I think before
we
go into—
Technically all you'd have to say is אחת, achas, אחת ואחת, achas
ve'achas, and then you'd go שתיים, shtayim, שלוש. shalosh.
That's true too. And just שלא יטעה, shelo yiteh, which might be
why Rashi says it's also partly not to slow -- just partly
to slow them down. Okay, יצא והניחו על כן הזה שבהיכל. yatza
vehinnicho al can hazeh shebaheichal. Now he's done with that and he
puts it on the on the pedestal in the היכל, Heichal, the
gold pedestal. תנן התם. tenan hatam. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer,
לא היו שופרות לקני חובה מפני התערובת. lo hayu shofaros lekinei chova
mipnei hata'aroves.
So this is coming from left field, you might remember this from
שקלים. Shekalim. Rabbi Yehuda said, remember there's -- that they had these
thirteen שופרות shofaros in the בית המקדש like צדקה tzedakah boxes, you
know, horns that you would put the money in for different purposes.
And one of them was for bird sacrifices that had to be
obligatory, one for a חטאת, chatas, one is an עולה, olah, if
you brought at the end of a טהרה taharah process like a
woman who was a יולדת yoledes or זבה, zava, etc. It could
be a man as well. So he would say there would not
be a thing there for the for the obligatory birds because of
because of mixtures. מאי תקנת התערובת? mai takanas hata'aroves? What does it
mean mixtures? אמר רב יוסף amar Rav Yosef מפני תערובת חובה בנדבה
mipnei ta'aroves chova bindavah because you might accidentally get the money that
was given for the obligatory birds which is half חטאת, chatas, half
עולה olah -- I mean one חטאת, chatas, one עולה, olah, the
money is split, mixed up with the money that's in the שופר
shofar for just for the free-will birds. And then there'll be money
of a חטאת chatas mixed up with money of an עולה. olah.
So אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, so Abaye says I don't
understand why that would be a problem. ונעביד תרי, vunaavid terei, have
two different שופרות shofaros ונכתוב עלייהו venichtov aleihu האי דחובה והאי דנדבה.
hai dechova vehai dendavah. Write on it! This is the שופר shofar
for חובה, chova, this is one for נדבה. nedavah. גמרא says no,
רבי יהודה לית
ליה כתיבה. Rabbi Yehuda leis lei kesivah. Rabbi Yehuda doesn't believe in
writing. Now what it means is because רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir was
the סופר sofer and Rabbi Yehuda was the one who always argued
-- Rabbi Meir was a סופר. sofer. Anyway, but what it means
is Rabbi Yehuda doesn't think that you can trust the writing to
mean that people will pay attention. You can't say, we'll just --
we'll just write it on the thing! No, I don't believe in
that. Why? How do you know that? דתנן, detnan, רבי יהודה אומר,
Rabbi Yehuda omer, לא היה שם אלא כן אחת בלבד. lo haya
sham ela can achas bilvad. So Rabbi Yehuda said there was only
one pedestal for the gold for the blood of the ox and
the blood of the goat. So תרי מאי טעמא לא, trei mai
taama lo, why not two pedestals? משום דמחלפי, mishum demichalfei, because if
you have one pedestal that you have the one of the ox
and the one that you have the blood of the goat on
it, so you'll get confused. Wait, which is the ox, which is
the goat? So you'll pick up the wrong one. ונעביד vunaavid --
so גמרא says why is that why is that a good reason?
ונעביד תרי ולכתוב עלייהו vunaavid terei velichtov aleihu האי דפר והאי דשעיר.
hai depar vehai desair. Make two pedestals, have one pedestal say ox
and the other have a sign that says goat. אלא רבי יהודה
לית ליה כתיבה. ela Rabbi Yehuda leis lei kesivah. Rabbi Yehuda must
believe that you can't trust that. So therefore if you have only
one pedestal, you can't get it confused because you come out with
the, you know, with the, you know, with the goat blood and
that's in your hand and you've got to sort of -- there's
only room for one of them, so you take off the ox
blood, you put down the goat blood, you know, then you do
the ox. And then when you come back you switch it the
other way. Well, so maybe. Anyway, but if there's only one and
only room for one. Now of course you could take one in
one hand and say wait, which is which? But presumably not. You're
in the process of taking one off and putting one down and
therefore he says that you won't get -- that'll make it clear
which is which. If you actually have an opportunity to put them
down and turn away and come back, you'll get confused. And you
can't trust -- you can't trust writing. Now of course if you
can't trust writing, how do you have thirteen שופרות shofaros at all?
Meaning they're
they're all for something different. How come it is that only the
bird
ones
you'll get mixed up and you can't trust the writing? I don't
right, I don't know. Right, I don't know how they get distinguished
in other ways that that's not a problem, but דווקא davka one
for חובה chova and one for נדבה, nedavah, that is a problem.
Well there's just no extrinsic system that is human-proof. Right. It's all
about your concentration.
Right, but Michael is right. Color would be a lot better, you
know, color, height, other differences and something written. Yeah.
I'll just put this one down on the red one just for
a minute. Right. Okay, at any rate you're confused.
All right, so that explains why Rabbi Yehuda says only one, it's
connecting these two positions of Rabbi Yehuda. So the גמרא says okay,
so that's a nice way to connect these two positions of Rabbi
Yehuda, but the גמרא is not buying. מיתיבי, meisivei, I'll ask you.
מיתיבי. meisivei. שלשה עשר שופרות היו במקדש, shelosha asar shofaros hayu bamikdash,
thirteen. והיה כתוב עליהם vehaya kasuv aleihem was written on them תקלין
חדתין, taklin chadatin, new shekels, תקלין עתיקין, taklin atikin, old ones if
you're paying last year's taxes, last year's shekels, קינין, kinin, bird sacrifices,
גוזלי עולה, gozlei olah, also birds but these are turtledoves,
pigeons, one is one, was the other, עצים, eitzim, wood sac --
you know, donations for wood, לבונה, levonah, incense, you could actually give
a נדבה nedavah of incense, which is a whole big חידוש chiddush
by the way I should mention for when we learned this in
שקלים Shekalim I mean this was a while, there's nowhere in the
תורה Torah it says you can do a private donation of incense,
but חז"ל Chazal say you can and you would burn that incense,
the private donation on the outer מזבח. mizbeach. So you actually get
three different locations for the incense. Right, the normal daily incense in
the בית המקדש. Twice a day was on the gold altar in
the היכל, Heichal, on יום כיפור was in the קודש קדשים, Kodesh
Kodashim, and a personal donation would be on the outer altar. So
since there's all this focus on the burning of incense, I wanted
to just point that out, that that's fascinating, three different types and
three different locations. Okay, so that's the incense. וזהב לכפורת, V'zahav l'kapores,
and you could donate gold for the כפורת, kapores, which is strange.
The כפורת kapores didn't need gold, it was already made. So רש״י
Rashi says כפורת kapores means for the כלי שרת. klei shares. ושבע,
V'sheva, so that was seven. וששה לנדבה, V'shisha l'nedava, and six for
just free will עולות, olos, you know, a lot of money that
couldn't be used in other ways finally funneled its way into this
נדבה nedava when there were no sacrifices being brought on the מזבח.
mizbeach. So anyway, so what are these? תקלין חדתין אלו שקלים של
כל שנה ושנה, Taklin chadetin elu shekalim shekol shana v'shana, that's the
yearly שקל. shekel. תקלין עתיקין, Taklin atikin, the old ones. מי שלא
שקל ישקול, Mi shelo shakal yishkol, if you didn't give your שקל
shekel last year, ישקול לשנה הבאה, yishkol l'shana haba, you can still
give it next year. קינים הן תורים, Kinim hein torim, the קינים
kinim are the bird sacrifices which is the תור, tor, I think
that's the pigeons. וגוזלי עולה הן בני יונה, V'gozlei ola hein b'nei
yona, which is the turtle dove. I think that they're really very
related, if not the same species. Anyway, כולם עולות, kulam olos, and
they were all עולות, olos, דברי רבי יהודה. divrei Rabbi Yehuda. That's
what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says because he did not believe that
there was a separate שופר shofar for חובה. chova. So now why
is this the problem? Because just be accurate and consistent, he says.
Right, he says they're all עולות, olos, there's no חובה. chova. No,
because he says the way they were distinguished was different things were
written on them. So clearly he believes, which is what we said
before. How can you say the only problem with the bird חובה
chova and the bird עולה ola is you can't trust writing? How
do you distinguish the thirteen? And here you see that רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says you had different things written on all the thirteen.
So you can't say רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda doesn't trust writing. So
anyway, so what is, so we'll just read one sentence, what the
reason is and we'll explore this tomorrow. So what is the reason
that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda did not have two different things for
birds of חובה chova and birds for the נדבה? nedava? So כי
אתא רב דימי אמר אמרי במערבא, Ki ata Rav Dimi amar amri
b'ma'arava, they said in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, גזירה משום חטאת שמתו
בעליה. gzeira mishum chatas shemeisu ba'aleha. What we're afraid is that if
you just put money in not for into the שופר shofar for
your bird sacrifice and it's a חובה chova and the owner dies
and you don't know whose is whose, then you're going to be
bringing money a חטאת chatas from an owner who is dead, which
you are not allowed to do. So we'll talk about that tomorrow.
I didn't really explain that, but we will pick up with that
tomorrow. Okay.